<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: HBS_case_study | Hack hack hack...]]></title>
  <link href="http://adamjonas.com/blog/categories/hbs-case-study/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://adamjonas.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-09T08:55:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://adamjonas.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Adam Jonas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Optical Distortion, Inc. HBS Case Study]]></title>
    <link href="http://adamjonas.com/blog/optical-distortion-inc-hbs-case-study/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-13T16:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adamjonas.com/blog/optical-distortion-inc-hbs-case-study</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>ODI Discussion/Analysis Questions</h2>

<p>1)</p>

<ul>
<li>What characteristics of the ODI lens are likely to make it appealing/unappealing to farmers?

<ul>
<li><p>Appealing</p>

<ul>
<li>debeaking causes problems of their own in terms of the trauma it causes hurts short term production (for a full week, only 1 egg lost by 5 months) and in the long term in feed is wasted. Debeaking is not an exact science but reduced cannibalism to 9% from 25%.</li>
<li>for $2.50/hour could debeak approximately 220 birds per hour.</li>
<li>actually modifies behavior as opposed to reducing the weapon. Reduces cannibalsim to 4.5% (1/2 of debeaking)

<ul>
<li>225 birds an hour to put in lense</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>reduces feed costs from 24.46 pounds to 23.68 lbs per 100 birds

<ul>
<li>20,000 bird flock could save 156 pounds of feed per day ($12.324/day)</li>
<li>$158 per ton - $.079/lbs</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>unappealing</p>

<ul>
<li>more upfront cost</li>
<li>can cause eye infection/fall out of place</li>
<li>change from current practice.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>2)</p>

<ul>
<li>What is the value to famers of lenses over debeaking? Can you quantify it? (Hint: Think about savings from cannibalization, egg reduction, feed, and labor)

<ul>
<li>$.00073 a bird for the debeaking process (which would be unneccessary).</li>
<li>$.22 per bird feed savings over a hen's lifetime</li>
<li>$.108 in reduction in replacement cost of of $.21 since lenses reduces cannibolism by 1/2.</li>
<li><p>$.224 of added production in egg production. Hen lays 22 dozen eggs a year. If they lose a week of production from debeaking that is .423 dozen a week (which is 5 eggs a week) and if you assume that is $.53 a dozen that is $.224 cents of lost egg production per bird.</p></li>
<li><p>adds up to ~$.33 in added value per bird over their lifetime -> for large farms (50,000 birds) that $17,500 in added revenue a year (though it is annual cashflow of $12 million). For a small farm (10k) is it $3,500.</p></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>3)</p>

<ul>
<li>What Pricing policy should ODI adopt and why? What is the savings per bird for farmers at these prices?

<ul>
<li>need market acceptance</li>
<li><p>somewhere around $.35 per bird in added value, which would easily cover the $.07 price increase.</p></li>
<li><p>Skimming Price</p>

<ul>
<li>For products that represent a drastic departure from accepted ways of performing a service, a policy of relatively high prices coupled with heavy promotional expenditures in the early stages of market development (and lower prices at later stages) has proved successful for many products.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Penetration pricing

<ul>
<li>This policy is the reverse of the skimming policy in which the price is lowered only as short-run competition forces it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://hbr.org/1976/11/pricing-policies-for-new-products">Pricibg Strategies</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>4)</p>

<ul>
<li>Can ODI turn a profit at these prices?

<ul>
<li>sell at $0.08 per pair</li>
<li>cost $0.032 per pair + 12k (for first 15 million pairs)</li>
<li>cost $592,000 to operate</li>
<li>.048 per pair  in profit</li>
<li>592,000 / .048 = 12,333,333 lens to break even meaning they need .1% market penetration.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>5)</p>

<ul>
<li>How would you focus ODI's marketing efforts? How would you segment the
customer base?

<ul>
<li>345 farms have 20% of america's chickens. If they closed 4 of those farms they would be able to able to turn an operating profit.

<ul>
<li>crowded farms would benefit most from this change and the sales process would be easiest.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
