<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mac | Hack hack hack...]]></title>
  <link href="http://adamjonas.com/blog/categories/mac/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://adamjonas.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-27T15:02:50-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://adamjonas.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Adam Jonas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another new MacBook Air load]]></title>
    <link href="http://adamjonas.com/blog/another-new-macbook-air-load/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-12T13:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adamjonas.com/blog/another-new-macbook-air-load</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>RBENV</h3>

<ul>
<li>ran into a pow issue not recognizing my gemset -> similar <a href="https://github.com/37signals/pow/issues/202">issue to the one here</a> and <a href="http://thelucid.com/2012/10/11/pow-meet-rbenv/">here</a>.

<ul>
<li>it ended up because I had installed rbenv with homebrew which meant it was in the opts directory. What a pain.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the rbenv install went pretty smoothly save for that. Used [this as a guide](http://www.bounga.org/ruby/2012/02/06/pow-using-rbenv/.</li>
</ul>


<h3>PSQL</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>the install went much smoother this time. I used this <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12028037/postgres-app-could-not-start-on-port-5432/13847738#13847738">ref</a> when I ran into problems.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6867401/postgres-postgresql-fatal-database-ew-dev-does-not-exist">this helped</a> on my old air... the app installed without a hitch, but I was missing the creating of the databases.</p></li>
<li><p>when the psql app wasn't active</p>

<p>♕ psql
psql: could not connect to server: No such file or directory
  Is the server running locally and accepting
  connections on Unix domain socket "/var/pgsql_socket/.s.PGSQL.5432"?</p></li>
<li><p>after turning it on, I got this</p>

<p>♕ psql
psql: FATAL:  database "Ajonas" does not exist</p></li>
<li><p>the PATH clearly isn't right, but by adding <code>rake db:create:all</code> I got the app to bootup.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Bundler and Octopress reinstall</h3>

<ul>
<li>bundler wasn't recognized because of the different ruby version. Installed the new version and <code>gem install bundler</code> as [advised](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/7483515/rake-aborted-no-such-file-to-load-bundler-setup-rails-3-1.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MacPro Set Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://adamjonas.com/blog/macpro-set-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T13:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://adamjonas.com/blog/macpro-set-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><p>My postgres paths were screwed up. <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12028037/postgres-app-could-not-start-on-port-5432/13847738#13847738">This helped</a></p></li>
<li><p>need to install bundler for every ruby install</p></li>
<li><p>Pow path was screwed up. Need to create and set paths in <code>.powconfig</code> file.</p></li>
<li><p>needed to rm symlink for git completion per the discussion <a href="https://github.com/mxcl/homebrew/issues/16992#issuecomment-13162321">here</a></p></li>
<li><p>opens up the same terminal tab in a new window...</p></li>
</ul>


<p>```</p>

<h1>opens new tab in same dir</h1>

<p>precmd () {print -Pn "\e]2; %~/ \a"}
preexec () {print -Pn "\e]2; %~/ \a"}
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Loading up a new Macbook Air]]></title>
    <link href="http://adamjonas.com/blog/loading-up-a-new-macbook-air/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-19T10:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://adamjonas.com/blog/loading-up-a-new-macbook-air</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Avi helped me get my new Macbook Air rolling this afternoon...</p>

<p>Ruby 1.8.7 is the standard version that's loaded on the OS X Lion</p>

<p>Some lessons-- Xcode did not come loaded with the GNU Compiler Collection out of the box (AKA out of app store). (-bash: gcc: command not found) <a href="https://github.com/kennethreitz/osx-gcc-installer/">GCC Installer</a></p>

<p>Anyways this had to be loaded to run anything like Homebrew.</p>

<ul>
<li>All OSs except for window are a NIX: A Unix-like (sometimes referred to as UN<em>X or </em>nix) operating system is one that behaves in a manner similar to a Unix system, while not necessarily conforming to or being certified to any version of the Single UNIX Specification. (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix-like)</li>
</ul>


<p>Once it was installed we got the result: i686-apple-darwin11-llvm-gcc-4.2: no input files from the gcc command. (read more about gcc <a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Homebrew was installed from <a href="https://github.com/mxcl/homebrew/wiki/installation">here</a>.</p>

<p>-Homebrew replaced the old style of loading software which required configuring the config file since all OSs are customized with different versions. This is frustrating as hell. Jewelry box, RVM, and homebrew are powerful enough to take the grunt work out of the environment set-up, but can't the community find a way to wrap this in an app in the app store? Is this feasible?</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://jewelrybox.unfiniti.com/">Jewelry Box was installed</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/wget/">wget was installed</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred was installed</a></li>
</ul>


<p>We also modfiied the bash profile or dot files from Avi's github repository.</p>

<ul>
<li>He mentioned that in the future I should choose a user name with all lower case letters rather than the capitalized name that I chose.</li>
<li>I also needed to create a symbolic link for my sublime text editor so that I can call it from the command line (this is something I never figured out on my Fedora 15 system)</li>
</ul>


<h3>So for those keeping track at home:</h3>

<ul>
<li> GCC</li>
<li> Homebrew</li>
<li> Jewelry box</li>
<li> RVM</li>
<li> Ruby Update</li>
<li> Rails</li>
</ul>


<p>No MySQL or anything like that... until I need it.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://tech.xtremelabs.com/how-to-setup-your-mac-for-rails-development/">This is a good post on what to load up...</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/joshfng/railsready">rails ready script on github</a>)</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
